Guide to the Baldwin and Company Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Baldwin and Company papers
1818-1876
MS 56
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
49
A shipping firm based in New York trading with Europe, South America and various ports in the United States. The principal partner in the firm was Simeon Baldwin of New Haven. The records include account books, correspondence, papers dealing with the general business of the firm and papers dealing with the individual ships. The records for each of the 124 ships consist of bills of lading, manifests, freight lists, settlements of earnings, letters of instruction to captains, captain's accounts and other documents for each voyage. Two diaries are in the collection: Simeon Baldwin's business diary for 1821 and Charles Baldwin's diary of a voyage in the brig Duroc, 1830.
Baldwin and Company
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A portion of the papers were purchased in 1940 and 1944; a portion were the gift of Charles M. Baldwin, 1937.
Scope and Contents
BALDWIN & CO. COLLECTION
Bound Papers
Included in the account books are 3 day books and 5 journals, 1818-1831, lacking a few months in several years; 4 ledgers, 1820-1832, lacking July, 1823-March, 1827; 12 cash books, 1821-1838; lacking first six months of 1836; 3 sales books, 1820-1834, lacking 1822-April, 1827, and November, 1831-November, 1832; 4 sales memoranda books, 1823-1834; 2 accounts current, 1825-1832; Also included are 6 volumes of freight lists for the Regular Line, 1825-1834; 5 receipt books, 1827-1838; 1 storage ledger and 4 storage journals, 1825-1833; 3 volumes listing notes payable and receiveable, 1824-1831; and 1 volume listing bills payable and receiveable, 1831-1835; 9 volumes containing stubs of checks drawn on the Bank of New York, 1827-1840, and 3 volumes containing stubs of checks drawn on other banks, 1821-1839, lacking 1822-1832; 3 volumes containing stubs of notes drawn, 1825-1834; 9 volumes containing; stubs of freight receipts insured, 1824-1835; 2 volumes of the freight account of the Regular Line, 1825-1835. In addition there are several miscellaneous volumes viz: a small diary of business matters kept by S. Baldwin 1821; a small book containing Otis & Baldwin's account with the Merchants' Bank, New York, 1822-1823; a similar book with S. Baldwin's account, 1823; 4 small journal memoranda (3 of Baldwin & Spooner, 1825, and 1 of Baldwin & Forbes, 1831); a books containing amounts of freight lists for vessels on Regular Line and an account of disbursements for other vessels, 1825-1827; a small ledger and cash account of money spent on portage, 1827-1830; a book containing invoices of goods sent by or to Baldwin & Forbes, 1827-1830; a small book of freight and petty cash, 1828; a book containing a list of ships despatched from Boston, New York, and Philadelphia, with cargo, destination, and shipper, 1834-1836; and a small book containing S. Baldwin's account with the American Exchange Bank, 1847-1852.
Correspondence
The correspondence includes 10 letter books, 1822-1831, and 33 boxes of loose letters, 1818-1841 and undated, mainly from other mercantile firms located on the eastern and southern coasts of the United States, Western Europe and the Mediterranean, the West Indies, and ports in South America from Rio de Janiero north to Panama. A large share of the letters deal with the state of the produce market and include prices current for the various places. Others relate to bills of exchange, sales of goods, invoices, orders, and other business matters. There are also some letters from and (in the last box) to the captains of various vessels. There is in addition some correspondence in the papers dealing with individual ships.
Ships' Papers
The papers relating to ships (arranged alphabetically by names of vessels) consist of 19 boxes and deal with voyages to all the ports with which the firm traded. The papers consist of bills of lading, manifests, freight lists, shipping articles, settlements of earnings, consuls' clearances, port charges, disbursements, charter parties, bills of sale, letters of instruction to captains, bills for expenses, portage bills, protests, in cases where the cargo or ship was damaged, invoices and sales of cargoes, crew's releases and wage settlements, captains' accounts with the firm and the firm's accounts with the owners of the vessels and with agents in the various ports, and insurance policies. Following is a list of the ships:
[Ships listed in inventory, boxes 35-44]
Among the partially sorted miscellaneous papers are 6 more boxes, viz: one box of bills of lading for goods shipped by or to S. Baldwin, Baldwin & Spooner, Baldwin & Forbes or Baldwin & Co., 1821-1841, on vessels not included in the above list; of notes, drafts, bonds, acceptances, 1821-1839 and cancelled checks; 1826-1831; box of bills 1818-1841; of miscellaneous papers 1818-1841, consisting of memoranda, orders, receipts, account sales trial balances, accounts current, etc.; and one box marked A, containing insurance policies for cargoes and vessels, 1827-1831, not included in the previous list of ships; regimental orders, etc., 1827-1828, of 14th regiment New York State Artillery, the Governor's Guard, in which S. Baldwin was a captain; the accounts of Thornton & Treadway, 1825-1826; papers relating to the case of Higgins and Henshaw, for which S. Baldwin was one of the arbitrators, 1828; numerous miscellaneous legal papers; the Articles of Agreement to form the Regular Line of packets between New York and Philadelphia, 1824; a memorandum for the lease of a house, 1825; an agreement for the lease of a store, 1828; a list of American vessels loaded at Messina with cargoes of lemons and oranges, 1828-1830; a list of the value of foreign coins in U. S. money; a price current of "several articles for the present use...", ca. 1822; and a copy of the constitution and by-laws of the Independent Literary Society, 1819.
Biographical information compiled by Robert Randolph Greene, 1947.
[For more information, see also Mr. Greene's essay, "The American Merchant in 1830," in box 55.]
*****
Summary of "Diary of a voyage made in the Brig Duroc, 1830-1831" [See box 20]
Diary of a voyage made in the Brig Duroc, August 1830 - April 1831, by Charles Baldwin. The vessel had left New York in March of 1830 and gone to Gibraltar and Malaga before arriving at Rio de Janiero in August, at which point the diary commences. The voyage continued on to Trieste, Messina, Palermo, and back to New York. Also included are two pages describing the harbor and entrance procedure at Rio de Janiero, a list of duties on imports there, a description of the Royal Family of Brazil and a few notes on recent laws. Several pages are written on the quarantine regulations at Trieste, a description of the city, and an account of the weights and measures in use there. Also included are descriptions of Messina and Palermo, the weights and measures in use there, and the duties on imports.
Starting with Page 114 there follows an assortment of miscellaneous items including: Port Charges at Gibraltar, Malaga, Rio de Janiero, Trieste, Messina, Palermo, Port au Prince, Marseilles, Antwerp; a list of standard values of foreign currencies in 1821; "Remarks and useful hints relative to the Marseilles trade; Proformae for some goods purchased at Marseilles and sold at New York, 1828 and 1831; extracts from the Law of the State of New York relative to the inspection of Staves and Heading, and of Spirits; Harbor Regulations at Marseilles; an extract from a letter telling of the availability of brandies at Cette, France; Proformae of sales at Trieste and Marseilles, September to October 1831; copy of a letter from P. Eynaud, U.S. Consul at Malta, concerning the trade there, 1831; also a description of weights, measures, and duties there; Proformae of purchases at Malta, Marseilles and Cette, 1832-1833; a Rule for Compound Equations; quotations from Palermo, 1838; Statistics of importations of almonds, currants, muscatel raisins, and figs into U.S., October 1834 to September 1835; list of vessels sold at auction in New York, 1831; Statistics of importation and exportation of opium into and from U.S., October 1834 to September 1835; list of vessels on hand,1831, and those for sale or charter, with the price asked; a list of vessels chartered in New York; a description of the Grotto of Adlersberg, Garniola, Austria, written in 1833; three letters to C. T. Ralli from C. Baldwin, 1831-1832; copy of the form of a letter of Abandonment [of a vessel]; and a Table of Contents. [Several additional pages have been torn out]
Biographical / Historical
History of Firm
Simeon Baldwin, 1801-1872, of New Haven, Conn., went to Philadelphia in 1818 to learn the business of a merchant. He worked for his uncle, Daniel Barnes, until 1821, when he came to New York and started out on his own. In March of 1822 he formed a partnership with Samuel A. Otis under the firm name of Otis & Baldwin. This arrangement was terminated in June of 1823, Baldwin continuing alone until October, when he formed with Francis J. Spooner the firm of Baldwin & Spooner. This partnership lasted until February of 1827, when Spooner was bought out. In the following month Baldwin joined with Horace D. Forbes to form the firm of Baldwin & Forbes. Baldwin bought out Forbes in October of 1830 and continued the business alone under the firm name until the end of October, 1831. At that time Baldwin admitted his cousin, Sherman Day, and changed the firm name to Baldwin & Co., which continued until it failed in March of 1841. The following October Baldwin became president of the Jackson Marine Insurance Co. and later of the Merchants' Exchange Co. of New York.
Nature of the Business
The business of the mercantile firm was very wide, but consisted primarily of acting as commission agents. Transactions were done with firms in the chief ports of the United States, Europe, and South America. In 1825 Baldwin & Spooner inaugurated the Regular Line between Philadelphia and New York, a semi-weekly freight service by schooners and sloops of approximately one hundred tons. Baldwin & Spooner were the New York agents, while Bailey & Bridges managed the Philadelphia end. The line continued until 1835. Another large share of the business derived from acting as agents for various vessels. In this capacity the firm arranged for the collection of freight, made disbursements, and gave advice on the profitableness of proposed voyages. The firm also owned shares in various vessels for which they provided the cargo despatched on trading voyages.
Character of the Papers
The collection is divided mainly into four parts consisting of account books, correspondence, papers directly relating to individual ships of which the firm was owner or agent, and miscellaneous papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Business; Marine insurance; Merchant ships; Merchants -- New York (State) -- New York; Shipping -- New York (State) -- New York; Shipping; Ships -- Cargo; New York (N.Y.) -- Commerce; Account books; Bills of lading; Manifests; Diaries; Merchants; Baldwin, Charles, 1810-1870; Baldwin, Simeon, 1801-1873; Day, Sherman, 1806-1884; Forbes, Horace D.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814; Spooner, Francis J.; Bailey and Bridges; Baldwin and Company
- Inventory, (1818-1841)-1846, 1860-1876; 49' (14 flat gray, 40 paige, 1 black oversize, 1 folio)
  General note
  Folio
  - Letterbooks
    - 1822-1828 (Box 1)
    - 1828-1831 (Box 2)
  - Cashbooks
    - 1821-1833 (Box 3)
    - 1833-1838 (Box 4)
  - Accounts Current
    - 1825-1832 (Box 4)
  - Journals
    - 1823-1827 (Box 5)
    - 1827-1829 (Box 6)
    - 1829-1831 (Box 7)
    - 1831-1832 (Box 8)
  - Journal memos
    - 1825, 1831 (Box 8)
  - Journal of receipts and deliveries
    - 1828-1833 (Box 8)
  - Journal memo, 1834 (Box 8)
  - Ledgers
    - 1820-1823 (Box 9)
    - 1827-1829 (Box 10)
    - 1829-1832 (Box 11)
  - Sales books
    - 1820-1821 (Box 12)
    - 1832-1834 (Box 12)
  - Memos of sales
    - 1826-1834 (Box 12)
  - Check books
    - 1828-1833 (Box 12)
    - 1832-1836 (Box 12)
    - 1821-1822 (Box 12)
  - Journal, 1823 (Box 12)
  - Memo of sales and receipts, 1823-1826 (Box 12)
  - Sales book, 1827-1831 (Box 13)
  - Check books
    - 1821-1822, 1827-1828 (Box 13)
    - 1833-1839 (Box 14)
    - 1838-1840, undated (Box 14)
  - Bank books
    - 1822-1823, 1847-1852 (Box 14)
  - Freight lists
    - 1825-1826 (Box 15)
    - 1826 December (Box 15)
    - 1826-1828; Sailing register, 1826-1829 (Box 15)
    - 1828-1830; Sailing register, 1829-1841 (Box 15)
    - 1830-1834 (Box 16)
  - Freight receipts stubs
    - 1826-1833 (Box 17)
    - 1833-1835 (Box 18)
  - Freight lists and disbursements, 1825-1829 (Box 18)
  - Freight account, 1826-1835 (Box 18)
  - Cash received for freight Regular Line, 1825-1826 (Box 18)
  - Freight and petty cash, 1828 (Box 18)
  - Bills of lading stubs, 1824-1825 (Box 18)
  - Bills of lading stubs, 1825 (Box 18)
  - Invoice of goods shipped, 1827-1830 (Box 18)
  - Storage book, 1825-1829 (Box 18)
  - List of notes payable and receivable
    - 1824-1835 (Box 19)
  - Note stubs
    - 1825-1834 (Box 19)
  - Receipt books
    - 1818, 1827-1838 (Box 20)
  - Journal of receipts and deliveries, 1826-1828 (Box 20)
  - Day books
    - 1818-1823 (Box 20)
  - Account of postage money, 1827-1828 (Box 20)
  - S. Baldwin diary of business matters, 1821 (Box 20)
  - List of ships dispatched, 1834-1836 (Box 20)
  - Chas. Baldwin diary of a voyage in the Brig Duroc, 1830 (Box 20)
  - Domestic correspondence
    - 1818-1823 (Box 21)
    - 1824 - 1826 June (Box 22)
    - 1826 July - 1828 January (Box 23)
    - 1828 February - 1829 September (Box 24)
    - 1829 October - 1830 (Box 25)
    - 1831 - 1833 (Box 26)
    - 1834 - 1838 May (Box 27)
    - 1838 June - 1841 September (Box 28)
  - Foreign correspondence
    - 1826 (Box 28)
    - 1827 - 1829 July (Box 29)
    - 1829 August - 1831 (Box 30)
    - 1832 - 1833 October (Box 31)
    - 1833 November - 1835 July (Box 32)
    - 1835 August - 1837 May (Box 33)
    - 1837 June - 1839 (Box 34)
  - Shipping papers
    - Sch. Abigil, 1826-1827 (Box 35)
    - Brig Agenoria, 1827, 1829, 1831 (Box 35)
    - Sch. Alfred, 1831, 1835-1836 (Box 35)
    - Barque Amalia, 1841 (Box 35)
    - Brig Ames, 1828-1829 (Box 35)
    - Sl. Ann Hyndman, 1834 (Box 35)
    - Sl. Ann Maria, 1824 (Box 35)
    - Sl. Ann Strong, 1828 (Box 35)
    - Brig Arial, 1830-1831 (Box 35)
    - Sch. Bellona, 1825-1827, 1830-1832 (Box 35)
    - Brig Benj. Franklin, 1827 (Box 35)
    - Brig Benj. Valentine, 1830 (Box 35)
    - Brig Bogota, 1826-1828 (Box 35)
    - Sl. Boston Packet, 1824-1828 (Box 35)
    - Sch. Brandywine, 1828-1829 (Box 35)
    - Sch. Brilliant, 1834 (Box 35)
    - Sl. Brutus, 1824 (Box 35)
    - Brig Bunker Hill, 1825-1827, 1833 (Box 35)
    - Sch. Cadet, 1824 (Box 36)
    - Sch. Caravan, 1827 (Box 36)
    - Sch. Carpenter, 1832 (Box 36)
    - Brig Centurion, 1841 (Box 36)
    - Barque Chancellor, 1837-1839, 1841 (Box 36)
    - Ship Chancellor, 1827-1830, 1833-1836 (Box 36)
    - Sch. Chili, 1823 (Box 36)
    - Ship Clematis, 1831 (Box 36)
    - Brig Cuba, 1827, 1830 (Box 36)
    - Sch. Denny McCobb, 1831-1832 (Box 36)
    - Brig Delos, 1829 (Box 36)
    - Brig Duroc with Corres, 1829-1833 (Box 36)
    - Brig Eagle, 1830-1831 (Box 37)
    - Brig Ellida, 1835-1836 (Box 37)
    - Brig Empire, 1, 1840-1841 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Excel, 1826-1829 (Box 37)
    - Sl. Express, 1830-1831 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Frances, 1824, 1829, 1831 (Box 37)
    - Brig Frances, 1831-1833 (Box 37)
    - Brig Francia, 1827-1830 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Franklin, 1828-1834 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Gen. Elmer, 1830 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Gen. Warren, 1825-1827 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Geor. Gardiner, 1829-1830 (Box 37)
    - Brig Geo. Washington, 1831, 1834 (Box 37)
    - Ship Georges, 1832-1834?, 1835-1840 (Box 37)
    - Sch. Good Hope, 1829-1830 (Box 37)
    - Brig Hanford, 1835-1837 (Box 37)
    - Sl. Hannah Ann, 1824 (Box 37)
    - Brig Harriet, 1835-1836 (Box 38)
    - Sch. Harriet, 1829, 1833-1834 (Box 38)
    - Ship Henry, 1827 (Box 38)
    - Sch. Herald, 1823-1824 (Box 38)
    - Brig Hercules, 1827-1832 (Box 39)
    - Sl. Heroine, 1829 (Box 39)
    - Sl. Hiram, 1835 (Box 39)
    - Brig Hope Petriene, 1831-1836 (Box 39)
    - Sch. Horatio, 1830 (Box 40)
    - Sl. Hunter, 1832 (Box 40)
    - Sl. Intrepid, 1824-1825 (Box 40)
    - Sl. Iris, 1835 (Box 40)
    - Sl. Jane, 1827 (Box 40)
    - Sch. John, 1823 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Julia & Laura, 1830 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Lagrange, 1826-1827 (Box 40)
    - Brig Larch, 1828 (Box 40)
    - Brig Laurel, 1830,1832 (Box 40)
    - Brig Leader, 1825 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Leaper, 1824-1827 (Box 40)
    - Barque Louise, 1832 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Lucinda, 1826 (Box 40)
    - Sl. Majestic, 1824-1825 (Box 40)
    - Brig Marion, 1828 (Box 40)
    - Brig Marshall, 1837-1838 (Box 40)
    - Brig Martha Ann, 1830-1831 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Mary Ann, 1826, 1830-1831 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Meddle Not, 1830-1831 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Mirror, 1827-1828 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Morgiana, 1829 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Mt. Vernon, 1827 (Box 40)
    - Sch. Nestor, 1829-1831 (Box 40)
    - Sch. New England, 1834 (Box 40)
    - Sch. New York, 1827-1834 (Box 40)
    - Brig Orion, 1828-1830 (Box 41)
    - Brig Otis, 1829-1830 (Box 41)
    - Ship Pacific, 1827-1829 (Box 41)
    - Brig Panthea, 1826-1828 (Box 41)
    - Brig Paul Jones, 1831-1834, 1838-1841 (Box 41)
    - Sch. Peacemaker, 1831 (Box 41)
    - Brig Pheasant, 1827-1829 (Box 41)
    - Brig Planter, 1830-1831 (Box 41)
    - Sch. Potomac, 1830-1831 (Box 41)
    - Ship Queen Mab, 1828-1829 (Box 41)
    - Sl. Reaper, 1824-1827 (Box 41)
    - Brig Richard, 1829-1830 (Box 41)
    - Sch. Robert Staunton, 1829 (Box 41)
    - Sch. St. Croix, 1827 (Box 41)
    - St. Thomas, 1828 (Box 41)
    - Sch. Saluda, 1827-1835 (Box 41)
    - Brig Sicily, 1830-1832 (Box 42)
    - Ship Six Brothers, 1831-1832 (Box 42)
    - Sch. Socrates, 1825-1831 (Box 42)
    - Sch. Solar, 1831 (Box 42)
    - Brig Spartan, 1823, 1826-1828 (Box 42)
    - Brig Splendid, 1827-1830 (Box 42)
    - Brig Stranger, 1831 (Box 42)
    - Sch. Superior, 1828-1830, 1832, 1837 (Box 42)
    - Sl. Superior, 1824 (Box 42)
    - Brig Tampico, 1824-1827 (Box 43)
    - Sch. Thorn, 1826-1834 (lacks 1832) (Box 43)
    - Sl. Tiger, 1824 (Box 43)
    - Sch. Tobacco Plant, 1824-1825 (Box 43)
    - Sch. Torch, 1833-1835 (Box 43)
    - Sch. Traffic, 1831 (Box 43)
    - Sch. Triton, 1826-1834 (lacks 1832) (Box 44)
    - Sch. Two Sisters, 1829 (Box 44)
    - Sl. Union, 1829 (Box 44)
    - Sl. Venus, 1829 (Box 44)
    - Brig Vermont, 1829-1831 (Box 44)
    - Sch. Vernon, 1829-1830 (Box 44)
    - Sch. Volant, 1825 (Box 44)
    - Brig Washington, 1835, 1838 (Box 44)
    - Sch. Wm. Dawson, 1826-1828 (Box 44)
    - Brig Wm. Jones, 1833-1837 (Box 44)
    - Brig William & Thomas, 1831 (Box 44)
    - Brig Yellow Bird, 1828-1831 (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous [shipping] (Box 45)
    - Miscellaneous [shipping], 1818-1840 (Box 46)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1829-1841 (Box 47)
  - Bills and receipts
    - 1818 - 1829 (Box 48)
    - 1830 - 1841 (Box 49)
  - Notes, drafts, and bonds paid
    - 1821 - 1834 (Box 50)
    - 1835 - 1838 (Box 51)
  - Cancelled checks (Box 51)
  - ADD I
    - Correspondence, 1820-1845, [1861-1876] (Box 52)
    - Financial papers, 1824-1879 (Box 52)
  - ADD II
    - Correspondence, 1819-1841, [1846, 1860] (Box 53)
    - Financial papers, 1822-1841 (Box 53)
  - ADD III
    - Correspondence, 1820-1841 (Box 54)
    - Financial papers, 1824-1827 (Box 54)
    - Financial papers, 1828-1841 (Box 55)
  - ADDS IV - X
    - Correspondence and financial papers (Box 55)
      - Note: ADD X is Robert Randolph Greene, "The American Merchant in 1830" (senior essay, Yale University, 1947). Mr. Greene also arranged the papers and wrote the introductory description.
  - Miscellaneous oversize shipping papers (Box 56)